A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Projects FA733
Rockefeller Archive Center
- C-676: Tulane University - Plan for regional cooperation in higher education, 1958 (Reel P-1015)
- C-677: Stanford Research Institute - Study of world economic growth to 1980, 1958 (Reel P-1015)
- C-683: United Neighborhood Houses of New York, Inc. - Demonstration project in prevention and control of juvenile delinquency, 1958-1959 (Reel P-1015)
- C-684: Fellowship program in Economic Development and Administration (EDA), 1959-1960 (Ford Foundation initiated) (Reel P-1015)
- C-685: Syracuse University - Support for trial practice center, 1958 (Reel P-1017)
  Duplicate copies of this file are housed on reels P-1016 (Master Negative copy) and P-1018 (Duplicate Access copy).
- C-687: The Age Center of New England, Inc. - Cross-cultural study on attitude and conservatism in aging, 1958 (Reel P-1017)
- C-689: Claremont College - Summer session on Indian civilization, 1958 (Reel P-1017)
- C-690: University of Santa Clara - Educational needs of the professional manager, 1958 (Reel P-1017)
- C-692: Chicago Natural History Museum - Exhibitions of primitive art, 1958 (Reel P-1017)
- C-693: Chicago Natural History Museum - Cataloging projects of division of Asiatic archeology and ethnology, 1958 (Reel P-1017)
- C-694: Council of Mexican-American Affairs - Support for social agency to service Mexican-Americans, 1958 (Reel P-1017)
- C-695: Faculty Research Fellowships - Social Science and Business (Ford Foundation initiated), 1958 (Reel P-1017)
- C-697: Mathematical Association of America - Preparation of an encyclopaedia of mathematics, 1958 (Reel P-1017)
- C-698: International Institute for the Study of Religions in Japan - Support for development of program, 1958 (Reel P-1017)
- C-699: Government of Pakistan - Agricultural research and education, 1958-1963 (Reel P-1017)
- C-700: American Institute of Physics - Improvement of physics teaching in America, 1958 (Reel P-1017)
- C-701: National Opinion Research Center (University of Chicago) - Research proposal regarding the aged, 1958 (Reel P-1017)
- C-702: Office of the Member for Education and Social Services, Lusaka, Northern Rhodesia - Establishment of Polytechnic for Lusaka, Northern Rhodesia, 1958 (Reel P-1017)
- C-703: Tsuda College, Tokyo, Japan - Research institute for language teaching and linguistic studies, 1958 (Reel P-1017)
- C-704: Fodd Production Suervy - Pakistan / Consultants in Food Production Program - Pakistan, 1958-1963 (Reel P-1017)
- C-705: University of Chicago - Center for advanced study in mathematics, 1958 (Reel P-1017)
- C-706: University of California, Berkeley - Western regional conference of university and college teachers of labor economics and industrial relations, 1958 (Reel P-1017)
- C-709: Educational Testing Service - Study executive reactions to management problem situations on sound film, 1958-1959 (Reel P-1017)
- C-710: Syracuse University Research Institute - Effect of the antitrust laws on mass media, 1958 (Reel P-1017)
- C-711: Mathematical Association of America - Establishment of Washington, DC office, 1958 (Reel P-1017)
- C-712: Baylor Theatre - Experiment in dramatization, "Of Time and the River" by Thomas Wolfe, 1958 (Reel P-1017)
- C-714: American Council of Learned Societies - Committee on Uralic and Altaic studies (Reel P-1017)
- C-717: Lehigh County Community Council - Survey of the older worker, 1958 (Reel P-1017)
- C-718: University of Virginia - Social Science research, 1958 (Reel P-1017)
- C-719: University of Chicago - Working seminar of urban geographers, 1958-1959 (Reel P-1017)
- C-720: American Academy of Arts and Sciences - Support for special issue of "DAEDALUS" on the visual arts, 1958 (Reel P-1017)
- C-723: University of Maryland - Three year study of "The Patterns of Invention", 1958-1959 (Reel P-1017)
- C-725: University of Illinois - Economic research project, 1958 (Reel P-1017)
- C-729: Blaisdell Institute for Advanced Study in World Culture and Religions - General program, 1958 (Reel P-1017)
- C-732: "Bootstrap" program to improve teaching and encourage research in less prominent schools of business and departments of business administration (Ford Foundation initiated), 1957-1958 (Reel P-1017)
- C-734: San Diego State College - Study of problem of free time in later life, 1958-1959 (Reel P-1017)
- C-735: Columbia University - Preservation of the John Jay papers, 1958-1959 (Reel P-1017)
- C-736: United States National Student Association - Exchange of Polish and American students, 1958 (Reel P-1017)
- C-737: Governmental Affairs Institute - Training within industry institute for Iran, 1958-1962 (Reel P-1017)
- C-738: American Society of Criminology - Study the teaching and research of criminology in the United States, 1958 (Reel P-1017)
- C-740: Institute of International Education - Study tour of Soviet Union by Executive Committee of National Governors, 1958-1959 (Reel P-1017)
- C-741: Evaluation of "Continental Classroom" (Ford Foundation initiated) (Reel P-1017)
- C-742: Dartmouth College - Program to strenghten mathematical teaching and research, 1958-1960 (Reel P-1017)
- C-744: International City Managers' Association - Clearing house on training methods, programs and materials, 1958 (Reel P-1017)
- C-745: University of Michigan - Interdisciplinary program of research in public relations, 1958-1959 (Reel P-1017)
- C-747: University of Miami - Student tutor teaching study system, 1958 (Reel P-1017)
- C-750: Western College for Women - Support for program of intercultural studies, 1958-1963 (Reel P-1017)
- C-756: Marquette University - Conference on land tenure, industrialization and social stability, 1958 (Reel P-1017)
- C-758: Iowa State College - Support for agricultural adjustment, 1958-1959 (Reel P-1017)
- C-759: University of Michigan - Graduate fellowship awards to law teachers, 1958-1959 (Reel P-1017)
- C-761: European Foundation for International Exchange - Exchange of students and civil servants of countries of European economic community, 1958-1959 (Reel P-1017)
- C-763: University of Helsinki - Study of conceptions of social class adn political attitudes in Finland, 1959 (Reel P-1017)
- C-764: Tulane University - Educational television credit course program, 1958-1959 (Reel P-1017)
- C-766: Ford Foundation - International Training and Research (ITR) - Bibliography and teaching aids for non-western studies, 1959 (Reel P-1019)
- C-768: American Association of Land-Grant Colleges and State Universities; State Universities Association - Study of state universities and land-grant institutions, 1959 (Reel P-1019)
- C-772: Appraisal of activities of major agencies to further economic and social development in Latin America (Ford Foundation initiated), 1958 (Reel P-1019)
- C-774: University of California, Los Angeles - First year foreign study fellowship program in business administration, 1959 (Reel P-1019)
- C-777: University of Chicago - International conference on Latin American literature, 1959 (Reel P-1019)
- C-778: University of Arkansas - Graduate program in business administraion and economics, 1958-1959 (Reel P-1019)
- C-779: Lehigh University - Teaching of the principles of conomics, 1959 (Reel P-1019)
- C-785: Rand Corporation - Fellowships in defense studies, 1959 (Reel P-1019)
- C-787: Southern Methodist University - Department of Economics, 1959 (Reel P-1019)
- C-788: United States National Student Association - Civic and social responsibility, 1959 (Reel P-1019)
- C-789: Ministry of Education, Nigeria - Adult education exhibition at Zaria, Nigeria, 1959 (Reel P-1019)
- C-796: University of Chicago - Research on the formation of value structure in the contemporary state university, 1959 (Reel P-1019)
- C-799: American Council on Education - Problem of faculty compensation, 1959 (Reel P-1019)
- C-800: National Education Association of the United States - Program of juvenile deliquency research, 1959 (Reel P-1019)
- C-801: Humanities Research Council of Canada - Study of history and current developments of culture and letters in Canada, 1959 (Reel P-1019)
- C-802: Franklin Publications Inc. - Kabul, Afghanistan, textbook printing project, 1959 (Reel P-1019)
- C-803: Kyoto American Studies Seminar - Summer sessions in American studies, 1959 (Reel P-1019)
- C-809: Johns Hopkins University - Post-doctorate program in Department of Chemical Engineering, 1959 (Reel P-1019)
- C-810: North African student assistance (Ford Foundation initiated), 1959 (Reel P-1019)
- C-816: International House, New York - Support for program activities, 1959 (Reel P-1019)
- C-821: American Meteorological Society - Education and career development in meteorology, 1959 (Reel P-1019)
- C-823: Augustana College - Preservation of college collection of Swedish-American newspapers, 1959 (Reel P-1019)
- C-825: Aoyama Gakuin University - English language institute, 1959 (Reel P-1019)
- C-827: University of Pennsylvania; Educational Television Station WHYY - Television program in Russian and German language and American folklore, 1959 (Reel P-1019)
- C-829: University of Toronto - Research program in linguistics, 1959 (Reel P-1019)
- C-835: College of the City of New York, Guidance Laboratory and Counseling Center of the School of Teacher Education - Vocational and social outlooks among secondary school students, 1959 (Reel P-1019)
- C-840: Stanford University - Expansion of comparative educational activities program, 1959 (Reel P-1019)
- C-842: Metropolitan Housing and Planning Council of Chicago - Study of total cost of the total urban renewal program, 1959 (Reel P-1019)
- C-846: Loyola University, Chicago, Illinois - Summer workshop on teaching methods and techniques in schools of business administration and economics, 1959 (Reel P-1019)
- C-847: University of Texas - Research on judicial law-making and administration, 1959 (Reel P-1019)
- C-848: University of Kansas - Establishment of community theatre in state of Kansas, 1959 (Reel P-1019)
- C-849: Washington University, St. Louis; Health and Welfare Council of Metropolitan St. Louis - Negro and white aging in metropolitan St. Louis, 1959 (Reel P-1019)
- C-850: Kansai Economic Federation - Publication of "The Journal of Quantitative Economics", 1959 (Reel P-1019)
- C-852: St.Mary's University - Television presentation of modern mathematics, 1959 (Reel P-1019)
- C-855: Fellowship in business administration and economics, 1960-1961 (Ford Foundation initiated), 1959 (Reel P-1019)
- C-861: University of Michigan - Study of social interation among retired workers in the Detroit area, 1959 (Reel P-1019)
- C-862: Bucknell University - Program to strengthen engineering education, 1959 (Reel P-1019)
- C-867: San Jose State College - Spatial and ecological distribution of police hazards adn delinquency pattersn in a standard metropolitan area, 1959 (Reel P-1019)
- C-870: University of Pennsylvania - Symposium on civic design, 1959 (Reel P-1019)
- C-874: National Urban League, Inc. - Negro immigrant adjustment and leadership training, 1959 (Reel P-1019)
- C-879: Florida State University (FSU) - Fellowship program in Meteorology, 1959 (Reel P-1019)
- C-890: Research Institute for Management Science - Development of small industries in newly developing countries, 1959 (Reel P-1019)
- C-898: Nigerian Ministry of Finance, Nigeria - Economics for growing export crops, 1959 (Reel P-1019)
- C-900: DePauw University - Support for department of history (Reel P-1019)
- C-904: Thayer Academy - Center for far eastern and Russian studies, 1959 (Reel P-1019)
- C-910: Cornell College - Undergraduate research program in public policy, 1959 (Reel P-1019)
- C-912: University of Washington, Seattle - Atlas of the Soviet Union, 1959 (Reel P-1019)
- C-913: National Academy of Sciences; National Research Council - Establishing an office of education in the American Geological Institute, 1959 (Reel P-1019)
- C-914: University of Hawaii - Coordinated educational research, 1959 (Reel P-1020)
- C-915: University of Cambridge, Department of Applied Economics - Inquiry into the long-term growth capital in Great Britain, 1959 (Reel P-1020)
- C-917: European Productivity Agency - Research on the structure, functions and policies of trade unions, 1959 (Reel P-1020)
- C-918: Grants in Aid program for novelists and poets (Ford Foundation initiated), 1959 (Reel P-1020)
  Project description: "Program which will make it possible for creative writers, especially poets and novelists, to spend six months to a year in close working relationship with a limited number of theater and opera houses, both in the U.S. and abroad".
  1959 Grantees include: George Garrett – Alley Theatre, Houston; Herbert Gold – Actor's Workshop, San Francisco; Mark Harris – Actor's Workshop, San Francisco; Anthony Hecht – Actors' Studio and Phoenix Theatre, New York; Robert Lowell – New York City Opera Company and Metropolitan Opera Association; William Meredith – New York City Opera Company and Metropolitan Opera Association; James Purdy – Actors' Studio, New York; James Schevill – Theatre Workshop, Theatre Royal, London; Eudora Welty – Actors' Studio and Phoenix Theatre, New York.
  1963 Grantees include: Walter Clemons - Alley Theatre; William Eastlake - Actor's Workshop; Shelby Foote - Arena Stage; William Goyen - Lincoln Center Repertory Theatre and American Shakespeare Festival; William S. Merwin - Royal Shakespeare Theatre, Aldwych Theartre.
  See also Ford Foundation Grant files: 06000132 (PA60-132), Foundation-Administered Project (FAP), PROGRAM FOR POETS AND FICTION WRITERS; 06090149 (PA60-149), Foundation-Administered Project (FAP), COOPERATION OF THEATERS AND OPERA COMPANIES IN PROGRAM FOR POETS AND FICTION WRITERS; 06000513 (PA63-513), Foundation-Administered Project (FAP), PROGRAM FOR POETS AND FICTION WRITERS; 06390514 (PA63-514), Foundation-Administered Project (FAP), COOPERATION OF THEATERS AND OPERA COMPANIES IN PROGRAM FOR POETS AND FICTION WRITERS.
- C-920: Program Specialists (India): Consultants on national service scheme (Ford Foundation initiated), 1959 (Reel P-1020)
- C-921: Program Specialists and Consultants (India): Business management (Ford Foundation initiated) (Reel P-1020)
- C-922: New York Pro Musica Antiqua - Experiment in recreating musical sounds and performing styles of the high renaissance, 1959 (Reel P-1020)
- C-925: Council for the Advancement of Small Colleges, Inc. - General program, 1959 (Reel P-1020)
- C-928: Royal Anthropologial Institute of Great Britain and Ireland - Research in the Guiana region of South America, 1959 (Reel P-1020)
- C-930: British Institute of International and Comparative Law - Survey of administration of justice in British Africa, 1959 (Reel P-1020)
- C-931: Program for [Orchestra] Conductors (Ford Foundation initiated) (Reel P-1020)
- C-934: Grants to teams of theater designers (Ford Foundation initiated), 1959 (Reel P-1020)
  See also: Ford Foundation records, Grants, 06090148 (PA60-148), Foundation-Administered Project (FAP), "PROGRAM FOR ARCHITECTS AND THEATER DESIGNERS".
  See also: Ford Foundation records, Grants, 06100261 (PA61-261), The American Federation Of Arts, Inc., "EXHIBITION AND PUBLICATION OF DESIGNS AND MODELS RESULTING FROM THE FOUNDATION'S PROGRAM FOR THEATER DESIGN".
  Project description: "Grants-in-aid program to about five teams to theater people headed by a designer who would carry the project through to the drafting and model stage, and perhaps then come together in an exhibit to be assisted by the Ford Foundation".
  Grantees include:
  Ralph Alswang (designer) and Paul Rudolph (architect), – development of a theater using new film projection techniques and live stage action simultaneously.
  Eldon Elder (designer) and Edward Durell Stone (architect) – design of a 2,000 seat outdoor theater.
  Barrie Greenbie (designer) and Seth Hiller (architect) – design of an ideal theater for the modern dance.
  David Hays (designer) and Peter Blake (architect) – design of a 299 seat open-stage theater.
  George C. Izenour (designer) and Paul Schwikher (architect) – development of a theater complex comprising one theater convertible among proscenium, Elizabethan, and arena-stage forms, and an experimental space controlled by an analogue and digital computer.
  Frederick J. Kiesler (architect and designer) working with playwrights and mechanical engineers – design of a flexible urban theater adaptable to both classical and experimental plays.
  Jo Mielziner (designer) and Edward L. Barnes (architect) – design of an ideal theater to house 'intimate music-drama' outside the traditional operatic and musical-comedy forms.
- C-937: National Planning Association; Stanford Research Institute - Factors affecting capital investment in tropical Africa, 1959 (Reel P-1020)
- C-940: University of Kentucky - Collection of Indonesian material culture, 1959 (Reel P-1020)
- C-941: Asia Society, Inc. (New York) - Travelling exhibitions of Asian art, 1959 (Reel P-1020)
- C-943: University of Dacca, Pakistan - Program of research and teaching in linguistics, 1959 (Reel P-1020)
- C-944: University of South Florida - Experimental program of advanced basic studies, 1959 (Reel P-1020)
- C-945: University of Washington, Seattle - Visiting lecturers in mathematics, 1959 (Reel P-1020)
- C-949: Univesity of Michigan; University of Michigan Press - Publication of outstanding works in contemporary Russian literature, 1959 (Reel P-1020)
- C-950: University of New Mexico - Relation of study of philosophy to success in business, 1959 (Reel P-1020)
- C-952: Kansas State College of Pittsburg - Research investigation of teacher education, 1959 (Reel P-1020)
- C-954: University of Hawaii - Race relations research, 1959 (Reel P-1020)
- C-959: New York University - Educational film on relationships between African sculpture and aspects of African daily life, 1959 (Reel P-1020)
- C-960: Institute of International Education - Series of seminars on Soviet Union, 1959 (Reel P-1020)
- C-965: Program Specialists and Consultants (India): Adviser on agricultural development, 1959 (Reel P-1020)
- C-967: Duke University - Assistance for small college teachers to complete their Ph.D. programs, 1959 (Reel P-1020)
- C-971: University College of the West Indies - Extra mural program, 1959 (Reel P-1020)
- C-973: University College of the West Indies - In-service training in public administration, 1959 (Reel P-1020)
- C-974: Engineering faculty strenghening (Ford Foundation initiated), 1959 (Reel P-1020)
- C-976: Experimental programs for engineering faculty recruitment and development (Ford Foundation initiated), 1959 (Reel P-1021)
- C-977: Science program (Ford Foundation initiated), 1959 (Reel P-1021)
- C-978: Institute of International Education - Conference on the educational needs of Africa (Reel P-1021)
- C-980: Greek Atomic Energy Commission - Fellowship program for Greece, 1959 (Reel P-1021)
- C-983: University of Oklahoma - String music instruction program in Oklahoma public schools, 1959 (Reel P-1021)
- C-990: University of Vermont - Study of regrouping of students for mathematics in rural schools, 1959 (Reel P-1021)
- C-992: Faculty exchanges between American and Soviet Universities, 1959 (Reel P-1021)
- C-993: University of Wisconsin - Establishment of a state orchestra for Wisconsin, 1959-1960 (Reel P-1021)
- C-994: Faculty research fellowships in social science and business, 1960-1961 (Ford Foundation initiated), 1959 (Reel P-1021)
- C-996: Governmental Affairs Institute - Regional seminars to be conducted in different parts of the United States, 1959 (Reel P-1021)
- C-997: American Arbitration Association - Labor arbitration awards to libraries of universities and law schools, 1959 (Reel P-1021)
- C-998: Cornell University - Development of graduate education and research in public administration, 1959 (Reel P-1021)
- C-1000: State University of Iowa - Research in field of aging, 1959-1960 (Reel P-1021)
- D-5: Tulane University - Training program for teachers of engineering, 1959 (Reel P-1021)
- D-6: Oregon State Sustem of Higher Education - Development of educational television in Oregon, 1959 (Reel P-1021)
- D-7: Department of Corrections, State of California - Pilot study of parole supervision, 1959-1963 (Reel P-1021)
- D-10: Northeastern Illinois Metropolitan Area Planning Commission - Study of metropolitan plans for flood control, 1959 (Reel P-1021)
- D-11: Northeastern Illinois Metropolitan Area Planning Commission - Studies for metropolitan water supply policy and program, 1959 (Reel P-1021)
- D-13: Northeastern University - Small business manpower problems, 1959 (Reel P-1021)
- D-14: Xavier University - New format for language readers, 1959 (Reel P-1021)
- D-17: Health and Welfare Council of Seattle and King County - Community organization and planning for the aged, 1959 (Reel P-1021)
- D-20: Demonstration projects to develop and improve community programs for older people (Ford Foundation initiated), 1959 (Reel P-1021)
- D-22: Fellowship program for non-academic scholars in the creative arts (Studies in the Creative Arts), 1959 (Reel P-1021)
  See also: Ford Foundation records, Grants, 06090249 (PA60-249), Foundation-Administered Project (FAP), "PROGRAM FOR STUDIES IN THE CREATIVE ARTS".
  1959 Grantees include: Florence E. Day; Antal Dorati; Edward H. Dwight; Mark Epstein; Martin Friedman; Noah Greenberg; Louise E. Jefferson; Newell Jenkins; Norton Juster; Edward Kook; Walter McQuade; John Peter; James P. Powell; Philip R. Randall.
  1960 Grantees include: Dore Aston; Sol Babitz; Marie Farnsworth; Robert Forth; Douglass Howell; Paul Mills; Philip R. Randall (renewal); Mary Rasmussen; Charles Shackford; Lee Simonson; Chester Sprague.
  1961 Grantees include: Boris Aronson; Nathan Broder; Ebria Feinblatt; David Flaherty; Ann Parker and Avon Neal; Gordon Rogoff; Jane Powell Rosenthal (renewal); Pauline Sommons; Felice Stampfle; Ikuyo Tagawa; Edward N. Waters.
  1962 Grantees include: Wayne V. Andersen; Sol Babitz (renewal); Louisa Bellinger; Harold Clurman; Mark Epstein (renewal); Marie Farnsworth (renewal); David Flaherty (renewal);Yvonne Hackenbroch; Avon Neal (renewal); Ann Parker (renewal); Denise Restout; Bernard Rudofsky; Susan Sawitzky; Eleanor A. Sayre; Ben Schlanger; Dorothy G. Shepherd; Parker Tyler; Charlotte M. Ullman.
  Includes correspondence with Lucy R. Lippard. See Rejections, 12/1961 and 1/1963.
- D-24: Monmouth College - Strengthen teacher education, 1959 (Reel P-1021)
- D-25: Government of Iran, Ministry of Finance - Establishment of financial planning and economic research in the Ministry of Finance, 1959 (Reel P-1021)
- D-28: Commission on International Rules of Judicial Procedure - Support for staff requirements for research and study program, 1959-1963 (Reel P-1021)
- D-30: Dissemination and utilization of professional knowledge in economics (Ford Foundation initiated), 1959-1962 (Reel P-1022)
- D-34: Marquette University - Imrpovement of the orientation of new college teachers, 1959 (Reel P-1022)
- D-38: California Probation, Parole and Correctional Association - Study to test the impact of controlled environment on deviant youth, 1959-1960 (Reel P-1022)
- D-39: Stanford University - Support for department of mathematics, 1959 (Reel P-1022)
- D-40: Western Michigan University - Social implications of sciences, 1959-1960 (Reel P-1022)
- D-45: University of California, Berkeley - Program of fellowships at Rome research center, 1959-1960 (Reel P-1022)
- D-46: University of Alaska - Establishment of a northern studies curriculum, 1959-1960 (Reel P-1022)
- D-47: University of Chattanooga - Program of three summer non-western culture institutes, 1959-1960 (Reel P-1022)
- D-51: University of Akron - Faculty exchange program between American and British urban universities, 1960-1962 (Reel P-1022)
- D-52: Lake Forest College - International Relations program, 1959-1960 (Reel P-1022)